so what is the difference between free
BSD and Linux you know that's what
people have been asking and the question
is um a big one to answer they're not at
all the same thing um they're both Unix
e Unix like operating systems they're
both absolutely operating systems and so
much so and they're both committed to
open source and free software and all
that up so much so that at the recent
Southeast Linux Fest um the free BSD
people were there the open FreeBSD
people were there with the Linux
conference even though BSD is not Linux
if there's one thing you take away from
this just know that in fact there's a
little bit of animosity in some circles
between the BSD people and the Linux
people um mostly from the bstd people
towards the Linux people uh bstd people
have usually nothing good to say about
the Linux project and the bloat that I'm
using their terms um and actually if you
want a really good person to ask about
BSD who spent a significant amount of
time embedded in the BSD community and
developing core uh things for it please
make sure to follow
lastore miles uh Dennis uh our Canadian
friend who is one of the greatest um in
my in my opinion one of the greatest
Technologies of all time is his twitch
channel is definitely not suitable for
work um you would not want young
children to watch it but you
know or or religious people may be
offended by his manner I'm not I think
he's amazing and um I regularly raid him
and he regularly raids me um but if you
want to know about you know all things
you know ogc and and BSC please make
sure you you talk to a BSD expert which
is not me um I'm actually really
intrigued by BSD I like to use it a lot
you see a lot of BSD pop up in systems
that require a lot of reliability um you
see BSD inside of uh router software and
um you
know router software and more router
software because anything that has a
high degree of um demand for security is
really there um and and so that I mean
that's pretty much it and that's where
you're going to see vssd um the
downsides of bstd are generally that um
they do not like a lot of change in fact
you really to justify as I hear it as I
hear it if you want to get something
added to the bstd kernel you I mean you
got to fight really really hard to get
anything in there and that's why
security people conscious people tend to
like BSD they are very very very
resistant to change they will change
they're it's not like they don't like
Improvement but they will not improve
something or make it better just because
right um BSD does come usually have uh
posix based tools um which include VI
like the vi program as opposed to Vim or
something you can't install Vim on it
but you know you just if you don't know
the difference between posix and
non-posix systems probably worth a video
watching a video about what that
difference is but BSD is very very
focused on posix Unix um I think it's
important to say as well before we leave
the BSD topic that BSD is a uh the basis
of Darwin which is um for a long time
actually when you looked at the UN name-
a to see what you know the system type
wasn't everything on a Mac like the one
I'm streaming from right now you would
see that it was BSD and it would report
as being a BSD system and that's because
jobs took BSD all the free software from
BS D and put it into uh you know put it
into the the the um um the next Cubes at
first and then eventually into all
macintoshes in fact I remember it was a
little quick story I remember
interviewing for a physici at IBM and
the guy giving me the interview was a
young guy and he was um he said what do
you think of Max that was actually his
first question I thought that was weird
and it turns out it's a long story we um
but he um um he wanted to get a Mac and
he wanted to make sure he didn't okay
hiring somebody who wasn't okay with
with getting a Mac for for IBM and IBM
had just kind of warmed up to using Max
and and adopting Max and I mean even
though they were big Power PC people
forever um and anyway so they go ahead
and uh and I told them I said well you
know it's good for for you know normal
users but in terms of developers and
stff I generally prer Linux he goes you
know that it's BSD now right I said no I
did not know that that that that was how
I learned that Mac had switched over to
BSD was actually in a job interview um
and and he said I said well he said
would you knowing that it's Unix is BSD
end of the hood would you be okay having
a Mac I said absolutely in fact I'm
going to go think about buying one right
now and and Darwin then they went you
know they proceeded to do a lot of
commits it turns out I regularly
criticize Apple for not giving back to
the community turns out they have been
but it's just been very quiet um I still
think that it's a little bit you know I
don't I
know sus that that you can't ask the
average Apple user do you know that
you're do you know you're using uh BSD
unic system and they don't know that
they don't need to know that but the but
you know at the same time the premise of
of Apple is the user shouldn't have to
know anything about their system they
should just know how to use their system
that includes the file system by the way
I have an entire story about someone I
tried to teach uh web development to who
couldn't understand hierarchal things
such as you know URLs and I try to
relate it to the Hier Aral file system
they had no idea what I was talking
about because Mac has completely hidden
hierarchal file systems from the average
user the point being that Apple doesn't
wear on their sleeve that they're Unix
and maybe that's okay um uh Apple has p
uh has paid a lot of money to become the
official um they become the the official
largest Unix distribution in the world
um built off of inex Cube and everything
so how does that differ from Linux I
mean that's almost just a what is BSD
kind of talk um but how does it differ
from Linux so the two the two actually
came about in completely different areas
uh lennus Tor bals is famously quoted as
saying if he had known that BSD existed
he might not have made um you know
started his his macr kernel project uh
which was an improvement on Minx which
his his Professor had made uh in Finland
so so SW wals who made
Linux um didn't know that there was this
other effort for BSD happening at this
same time to make a free version of Unix
and at the time I think it was AT&T Unix
um it cost you know something like
$2,000 uh per seat uh your name still
says Darwin did not know that oh does it
say Darwin now um I think it yeah um
anyway so uh the point is that that
these two free um versions of Unix uh
evolved independently of one another um
I am to be fair I'm not sure how many of
the commands uh the gnu Linux you know
that's where the ganu from G Linux comes
from stalman in the gang St stalman met
lennis Tor balds because T balds was
busy doing the colonel and then you know
he ended up uh Tor balds um ended up
saying fine let's just use all of your
utilities um that included um a bunch of
stuff including you know I think bash
and LS and you know all the commands
that that were designed to be unix's
equivalents came from the canoe project
and I think some of those made it into
the BSD project but I'm not sure um
while it is true that you can compile
them a lot of those projects for both
especially today in static you know
compilation mode but at the time you you
were dealing with different dynamically
linked libraries and stuff and and and
uh BSD had an entirely different set of
libraries uh C libraries and stuff for
from the ones that were used for Linux
um there probably was some crossover I'm
not I don't know um that would be a
question for uh probably for Dennis but
but my understanding is that the the B
Baseline systems were were sort sort of
the libraries were incompatible so so
you ended up getting these two
ecosystems it means you get two versions
of PS you get two versions of makor you
got two versions of of you know even
emac and things that stalman actually
wrote um but but in 2024 that has
largely that Gap has largely been you
know made small but there is one very
very significant difference between BSD
and Linux and if you take nothing away
from this video the people who waited to
watch the whole video are going to get
the most value out of this information
right now Linux created lxc lxc stands
for Linux
containers and Docker is
largely you know pretty icing on the
cake of lxc it makes lxc approachable by
Common People that that's people deep
you know Linux gurus out there they got
no love for Docker even more so now
since docker's kind of you know done the
stupid things but but Docker at the
time uh was largely just a bunch of
utilities and happy you know
happy commands on top of lxc and the
hardcore people are like why can't you
just use lxc you know it's like I use
lxc by the way I don't even use Docker
or pod man I use lxc you know because I
am so you know OG so boss and but um
device will overhea the screen is
disabled in three seconds oh well so I
guess it's getting hot in
here so it's probably time to end this
video but the
lxc part of it was the distinction
because lxc became the basis of all
modern containers people in BSD world
love to say that they have these things
called jails which is their own
implementation of a container
architecture no one is using it I have
never even heard anybody for fun or
profit
using um those and I I'm not poking
holes I've talked with Dennis very
specifically said Dennis you know what
we need we need a translation layer
between lxc so that we can run
containers on BSD because as soon as you
can run containers on BSD the world of
containerization May open up but people
that run be you know the whole movement
away from containers and sort of toward
micr VMS is kind of interesting if you
don't know what a micr VM is you don't
know what a VM is a virtual machine you
don't know what a container is there's
different videos for that but this the
the point is is that you know the
ability to like have an Amazon Cloud
Server and click on a couple buttons and
have it just pop up which is which is
enabled by virtual machines and
containers that kind of thing um
kubernetes is all about containers and
if you haven't heard about kubernetes
yet um you will eventually if you
haven't heard about Docker at you will
those Technologies fundamentally depend
on Linux they are at the core Linux
Technologies you cannot have a container
that includes Docker on the desktop or
pod on the desktop those run micr VMS
running Linux so that you can get lxc
the biggest distinction between BSD and
Linux is lxc in my opinion um from a
pragmatic perspective from a perspective
of like why would I want to learn one of
the other um of course Linux is is got
much much more um you know adoption in
the industry by people that are doing
doing all kinds of things you're never
ever going to find somebody gaming on
BSD that's kind of silly I mean if you
find somebody please let me know but but
you know this whole movement Linux is is
much more in the user space and BSD is
very solidly in let's make the smallest
possible most awesomest uh Hardware so
computer Engineers love BSD uh you know
people who make routers love BSD people
who make um you know internet of things
kind of devices they love BSD and they
tend to avoid Linux because it's it's
it's much batter colel um I mean that's
changing but that's largely that's
largely the takeaway should you learn
both of them uh the pure belongs to unic
kernels I tend to agree should you learn
uh BSD as a part of your beginning
learning and the answer is no um you are
going to kind of by osmosis get it by
learning um you know when you learn uh
Linux especially if you learn it from
somebody who tells you not to use- p on
maker because it's not posix compliant
which is going to be how I do it then
you're you're going to to learn the
commands and stuff that will also from a
practical user perspective that will
work on BSD um but we are not going to
do any BSD work in the beginner boost
and it's largely a waste of your time if
you're a beginner trying to get into the
industry unless you're going to become a
computer engineer if you specifically
know you want to go for computer
engineering in which case you got to
learn Linux anyway so the Boost is still
relevant but after the Boost you would
want to layer on more knowledge and
you'd want to make sure you understood
BSD and other unises is that a thing
unix's right AIX Solaris um you know
these hpu I don't even know if that's
out there um sco there there are a bunch
of other Unix operating systems and you
know a lot of Linux people on the
internet don't even know that that there
are other systems in fact I won't
mention him but I remember one twitch
streamer uh being told that had to take
over a bunch of a Unix systems at work
from a bunch of old people old F farts
like me or older than me who are
retiring and he goes yeah I went to go
edit a file and there's this thing
called
V that's a true story and I I saw him
say that I laughed I laughed out loud at
my desk I was just having so much fun
with that and they're a fantastic person
they're such a good person and they're
so willing to learn new things and and I
I mean they didn't even know that VI
predated they' only know MIM that their
whole life that's all they'd ever known
because they grew up on Linux and
there's nothing wrong with that it's
just to to a guy like me that was a
little comical is like yeah what's this
V thing it doesn't have like all these
things I wanted from my vim and so so
knowing the difference and and but but
rest assured that if you're doing the
beginner boost with me um every single
thing we do when we do the beginner
boost is based on understanding the G
fact I've struggled with what to name it
whether we should name it Unix terminal
or the Linux terminal or get good with
Linux or get good with Unix or get good
with starx or whatever right because all
the stuff you're learning in the Boost
is relevant to all unix's uh other than
the containerized stuff right which
we'll learn at the very end every other
thing will work on BSD or AA or Solaris
and I dare say there's a lot of learning
that you could potentially do here on
YouTube or on Twitch that does not do
that it it's very Linux specific but
because I have such a strong background
in Unix in general in fact it was my fun
story um my mentor Joey uh when I was
first getting into all this stuff my
first experience with all of this stuff
was a Sonos machine and I actually said
to Joey I said man I wish I could get
Sonos at home it'd be so great for me to
learn it and he said and I quote well
you could always use Linux and I said
what's Linux I'll never forget that
moment I was I remember the room I was
in and that was the first time I heard
that Linux existed in something like 90
90s something I don't know what mid 90s
and and you know I went home and I
kicked the power PC I had a power PC Mac
and I installed Mack Linux and struggled
through all that my you know to get that
to work had I known about BSD uh I might
have given it a shop but Joey
recommended Linux Jo I don't know what
Joey even would have thought about BSD
if Joey had mentioned BSD I probably
would have installed you know BSD but
I'm not even sure how mature it was at
the time so the takeaway is it is
important that you know what it is so
you can talk about it you can know the
distinctions but if you learn Unix and
Linux correctly then you're you're
knowledge is going to translate between
the two and you don't need to sweat
about sweat it right now unless you're
going to become a specialist later on
but at the beginning stages don't freak
out about it that's it that's the end of
that video now I need to turn the stop
button here stop recording how was that
let's get some music